Guide to the University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1956-1972 UA.90.4.2
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh Division of the Natural Sciences Office Files
1957-1967
ULS Archives & Special Collections
University of Pittsburgh. Division of the Natural Sciences
UA.90.4.2
18.48 Linear Feet (44 boxes)
The Division of the Natural Sciences existed from 1956 to 1967 as one of three disciplines descended from the University of Pittsburgh's College, or School of Liberal Arts. These records from the office of the Dean of the Division of the Natural Sciences contain incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports, meeting and committee minutes, and other information about faculty, facilities, curricula, research, and other activities of the departments comprising the division.
History
In August 1956, Chancellor Edward Litchfield announced the reorganization of the University of Pittsburgh's undergraduate college into three disciplines: humanities, natural sciences, and social sciences. The purpose of these new divisions was to better focus departmental efforts on undergraduate and graduate education and support for the professional schools. Dr. Max Lauffer was appointed the first Dean of the Division of the Natural Sciences and in January 1964 he was succeeded by physics professor David Halliday. The Division of the Natural Sciences included the departments of Biological Sciences, Biophysics, Chemistry, Computer Science, Geology, Earth and Planetary Science, Mathematics, Physics, and Psychology, as well as Allegheny Observatory and the Scaife Radiation Laboratory. In October 1967, Chancellor Wesley Posvar announced that the divisions and the School of Liberal Arts would be reorganized to form the College of the Faculty of Arts and Sciences which was headed by Dean James Kehl.
Scope and Content Notes
These records were maintained in the office of the Dean of the Division of the Natural Sciences and contain incoming and outgoing correspondence, reports, meeting and committee minutes, and other information about faculty, facilities, curricula, research, and other activities of the departments comprising the division. In addition to material pertaining to the Division, this collection also includes reports and correspondence with other academic departments and schools at the University of Pittsburgh, as well as university-wide offices and initiatives.
Acquisition Information
These files were deposited by Margaret M. Vojtko, Dean's office of the Faculty of Arts & Sciences, on August 26, 1969.
Related Materials
University of Pittsburgh Division of Research in the Natural Sciences Office Files, 1930-1968, UA.90.4.1.2, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Chancellor of the University of Pittsburgh, Edward H. Litchfield, Administrative Files, 1956-1965, UA.2.10.1956-1965, University Archives, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Universities and colleges -- Administration -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Universities and colleges -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Records and correspondence; Administrative records; Correspondence; University of Pittsburgh. Division of the Natural Sciences -- Administration; Lauffer, Max A. (Max Augustus), 1914-; Halliday, David, 1916-2010
- Allegheny Observatory, 1958-1964 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Content Notes
  Budget; Devine accident; comments on student participation in history of observatory's relation with university; American Astronomical Society correspondence, finances and research done in 1960; Amateur Astronomers Association correspondence about equipment and insurance; course listing, Winter Trimester, 1961/1962; Frick endowment; proposed astrophysics programs; correspondence on condition of equipment; evaluation of programs and faculty at observatory; value of observatory to University; proposed construction of measuring machine.
- Allegheny Observatory, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Development plans; public relations problems; financial problems; closing decision; history of observatory; publicity about work at observatory; publicity re-closing.
- Allegheny Observatory, 1965-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  National Science Foundation (NSF) grant; publicity; description of graduate programs; letter from chancellor in Sky and Telescope advising observatory situation improved, April 1967; estimate for refurbishing basement of observatory, including photos; description of graduate study in astronomy at Pitt; list of publications, 1964.
- Biological Sciences, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Seminar notices; Staff conference minutes, August 1958-April 1959; correspondence on faculty appointments; correspondence on graduate assistants; announcements of graduate assistantships; letter on biological science graduate assistants being lured by Health Professions at larger stipends; department publications list, 1950-1959: new course offering in bacteriology, 1958; letter recommending botany, zoology and bacteriology be treated as separate departments; letter on standards for graduate study; letter on lab fees; correspondence about microscope use fee; letter on undergrad counseling; recommendations on undergrad curricula in Biological Sciences; report on conference by Communication on Educational policies; National Academy of Sciences, 1958; correspondence with physical plant on space and equipment needs; additions and alterations to Biology Sciences Department, Clapp Hall, including blueprint; correspondence about difficulties for researchers to work during holiday periods at Pitt.
- Biological Sciences, 1956-1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Announcements of lectures; staff conference minutes, August 1959-June 1960; letter regarding department morale; announcement of graduate assistantships; course listings and changes, fall and winter 1959/1960; correspondence on student involvement in curriculum planning; correspondence on instructional cost per student; program for M.S. and PhD candidates; correspondence with physical plant on space and equipment; lease from city of Pittsburgh for use of freezing compartment and furnace room in Engineers Building, Schenley Park, for use in plant virus research, 1960; undated draft of departmental personnel and equipment needs.
- Biological Sciences, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Correspondence on problems of delivery and inefficient A-V operators; minutes of staff conferences, 1960/1961; lecture and seminar notices; personnel in Biological Sciences; description of research on rubber conducted by Paul Mahlberg; list of staff and courses taught Winter 1960/1961; correspondence about plans to offer biology course on national TV; correspondence on problems with physical plant like space needs; estimated cost of lab alterations, Clapp Hall, 1960; report of Dr. Edward Stuart, Chemical Engineering, to Dean of Engineering on Report of Engineering-Science Biology Committee that engineering education should include biology, ecology and oceanography, 1960.
- Biological Sciences, 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Seminar notices; letter from Dr. Gray to Chancellor on lack of communication between administration and faculty, February 23, 1962; letter to Dean about accounting problems; letter from Dr. Buchsbaum for Senate Council on factors to low faculty morale; minutes of staff conferences, 1961/1962; notices of lectures; correspondence on problems with A-V equipment; correspondence about personnel; course schedule, winter term 1961/1962; report of student curriculum advisory committee on freshman courses for Biology I, fall 1960; correspondence on research; correspondence on parking problems.
- Biological Sciences, 1962-1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Seminar notices; minutes of staff conferences; letter of application for faculty position; correspondence on courses; course schedule, fall term 1963/1964; correspondence on current space assignment and availability including information on grants; general correspondence on department matters like space and equipment.
- Biology, 1963-1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Letter from Dean to Vice Chancellor of Academic Disciplines on merger of biochemistry research personnel; policy papers; letter on biochemistry research personnel; letter on cooperation between Biology department and Graduate School of Public Health; minutes of staff conferences, 1963/1964; notices of seminars on microbiology; inquires for positions in Biology; brochure on in-service institute for high school teachers sponsored by National Science Foundation; graduate study in biological sciences brochure; correspondence on plans for developing department; correspondence about invitation to Dr. Alfred Emerson of University of Chicago to lecture; correspondence on problem of delivery of equipment; suggested course list for biology majors; minutes of meeting of search communications for department chairman, March 24, 1964.
- Biology, 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Correspondence on department budget, April 2, 1965; seminar notices; minutes staff conferences; letter in Pitt News on good quality of Biology 80; correspondence on problems of undergrad advising; graduate study in biology brochure; copy of letter on proposed graduate degree in microbiology; correspondence on foundation support for Beta Beta Beta (biological honor society) meeting; letter from dean on rotating chairmanship; chairman of microbiology; correspondence on proposal for graduate degree program in microbiology; minutes of meeting of joint university group in microbiology, October 1964; correspondence on appointments in Biology Department, 1965; financial crisis affecting department; Dr. Gray appointed Avinoff professor; proposal for biology and biochemistry programs, October 1964; problems of biology 80 courses; correspondence on programs in biological sciences at University of California, Berkeley; copy of speech given by Curt Stern, Department of Zoology, University of California, Berkeley on diversity in biological sciences.
- Biology, 1965-1966 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  A prospectus on marine science at Pitt; correspondence on microbiology group; criticism of undergrad biology program by microbiology group and rebuttal by department chairman; minutes of staff conferences; seminar announcement; comparison of our Biology 15 course with Harvard; teaching Biology 80; reprint from Bioscience "Core studies for undergrad. majors" plus article from CUEBS News and "New Directions in Biol. Teaching" in Bioscience; correspondence on expenses for Beta Beta Beta convention; space in Clapp and Langley Halls.
- Biology, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Correspondence on insurance on plant research lab in Schenley Park; minutes of staff conferences; list of Biology Department staff; physical plant complaint; space problem; seminar announcements; change in Biology 80 course; biophone announcement; notes on Pymatuning lab equipment; letter on $2 million grant for life science and chemistry buildings; complaints about student records; proposal for PhD program in human genetics; program in environmental biology at Pymatuning; biography on new faculty appointments; letter from dean on split of microbiology group; correspondence about Biology 80 for School of Education Teacher Institute; correspondence on department problems.
- Biology, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Pamphlet on Oak Ridge travel lecture program; letters on two professors, editors of Biological Abstracts; possibility of research lab in Treasure Cay, Bahamas; recruitment memo.
- Biological Sciences - Pymatuning Laboratory, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Pymatuning program 1958/1959; note on lease fee for laboratory; fire insurance; administrators visit to lab; brochure on Pymatuning conference on ecology of fresh water organisms; proposed program for lab, 1960; correspondence with Pennsylvania Department of Forests and waters to erect buildings; brochure on lab; invitations to administrators for annual visit; correspondence on fish hatchery; letter about additional property; brochure, summer course in Ecology, 1961; invitations to administrators for annual visit, 1961.
- Biological Sciences - Pymatuning Laboratory, 1961-1964 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Correspondence about buying additional land; invitations, annual visit for 1961/1962 and 1962/1963; letter on NSF faculty fellowships; letter on Kent State classes using lab; list of value of buildings for fire insurance; correspondence on funds from the Nature Conservancy, Washington, D.C.; correspondence on charges to outside users; program of study and assistantships; letter on cost of winterizing lab; article by Rene Dubos on environmental biology in Bioscience; correspondence on developing lab program and facilities.
- Biological Sciences - Pymatuning Laboratory, 1964-1967 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Correspondence about progress; named changed to Pymatuning Laboratory for Ecology, 1964; annual administrative visit; High School Science Research Program brochure; brochures, 1966/1967; U.S. clean water restoration bill, 1966; correspondence on faculty housing at Pymatuning.
- Biophysics, 1958-1964 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Correspondence on status Dr. McConnell; parking problems; correspondence with physical plant; letter on good participation at international meeting of biophysicists; notice of assistantships; letter describing department program, March 8, 1960; correspondence on Dr. Anig as head of department executive committee; memo on curriculum development; letter on Mellon Institute personnel joining staff; suggested new faculty members; memo on Biophysics in Health area, June 20, 1961; department schedule of classes, 1961/1962; research assistantships brochure; search committee for new faculty member; class schedule, spring/summer 1962/1963; description of Biophysics 267; information sheet on department programs; correspondence on Dr. Xanig, Chairman; fall schedule, 1963/1964; brochure on biophysics 81; pictures of department facilities.
- Biophysics, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Fall schedule; brochure on Biophysics 81; filing instructions for: Dr. Lauffer's editorial duties, for photos and slides, instructions on lectures, general files, etc.; instructions for handling office duties.
- Biophysics, 1964-1968 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Letters from Dr. Lauffer on acting chairman, 1965; seminar notices; memo on open-house, 1964; correspondence on space for Biophysics in Clapp Hall; memo on plant pathology research lab in Schenley Park; staff meeting minutes; joint seminars, Biophysics/microbiology, 1967; letters on "Center of Excellence;" Biophysics and microbiology proposed undergrad program; list of space needs; list of faculty and courses.
- Chemistry, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Colloquium announcements; Correspondence on Francis Clifford Phillips Medal in chemistry; Publication list, 1957/1958; Department Directories, 1958/1959-1959/1960; Correspondence about Theodore Cohen as consultant with Nuclear Science and Engineering Corporation; Correspondence on recruiting graduate assistants; Correspondence on summer teaching load; Renovation requests for Alumni Hall; Graduate assistant stipends; Correspondence R. Levine and E.H. Litchfield on trimester system; Correspondence about teaching load and salary of graduate assistants; Issuance of keys to Alumni Hall and renovation; Expenses in connection with installation of new helium liquefier; Laboratory changes in chemistry.
- Chemistry, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Seminar announcements; Letter from Princeton University about David Garvin as a possible Chemistry professor at Pitt; letter about Bottle throwing incident in laboratory; new courses available; laboratory accidents and student health service; Francis Clifford Phillips Medal in Chemistry; Renovation in Alumni Hall; Memo from Dean Lauffer to Dr. C.H. Peake on points of discontent among chemistry faculty; list of new students interviewed by graduate students; Advisement Communication; print-out of courses, winter trimester 1961/1962; request for chemistry library evening hours winter term; canceled courses; Society of Analytical Chemists of Pittsburgh awards; Chemistry Department awards; financial balance sheet.
- Chemistry, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Department organization and committees; representation in professional organizations; letter from E. Arnett to E. Garloch on the state of the library collection; copy of course listings for new Bulletin; Department directory; grade distributions; document describing proposed changes in course requirements; brochure "Graduate Work in Chemistry"; correspondence on poor facilities for Chemistry Department; memos on non-salary items in the Chemistry Department budget; correspondence about visit of noted chemist Dr. James Franck; student complaints about poor teaching; "Graduate study in Chemistry" poster and booklet; renovations to Alumni Hall; Handling of stockroom accounts; transactions, 1963; enrollment by course number; correspondence about Arthur E Juve for honorary degree; project descriptions.
- Chemistry, 1964-1966 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Proposed site for Chemistry building; renting space in Mellon Institute; Dr. Arnett's research group to move to Mellon Institute; use of Varsity Hall by Chemistry Department; "Graduate Study in Chemistry" booklet; revising Liberal Arts curriculum; distribution of studies courses; School of Liberal Arts Policy paper #2 degree requirements; refurbishing of Alumni Hall, new, chemistry building and dispersal of the department; separation of lecture and laboratory sections of Organic Chemistry courses; renovation of Alumni Hall; "Scope of Work for Alumni Hall-Fire Prevention" by J. Roling, May 1966.
- Chemistry, 1966-1967 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Renovation in Alumni Hall; request for additional space in Mellon Institute and State Hall; floor plan of State Hall, November 17, 1961; brochure "Announcing the 1967 College Chemistry Teacher Awards Program"; "Graduate Study in Chemistry" booklet; letter to Chairman W.E. Wallace from C. H. Peake on appreciation for turning down position at Illinois Institute Of Technology; visit of Pittsburgh Plate Glass personnel, November 1966; shorthand notes of department chairman meetings, January 20, 1966-May 4, 1967; employment of students as Federal Work-Study Employees; correspondence about space; Natural Science Facility, Phase I bids.
- Chemistry, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  Correspondence and memos on proposed interdisciplinary Graduate Degree Program in Human Genetics; "Reflections on the Graduate Student in Undergraduate Instruction," SLA Special Report #3, October 1966; "A Report on Student Evaluations of Academic Programs and Advising Practices," SLA Special Report #4, November 1966; capital construction program requested by the General State Authority, 1967-1973 figures by building; memo from acting chancellor Kurtzman on Ten year Development Needs; course print-outs listing students, November 18, 1966; increasing stipend for Andrew Mellon Fellows.
- Chemistry, 1966-1967 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  Personnel Memorandum no.78 "Minimum Wages and Overtime Pay"; list of clerical personnel whose salaries are below new entry note for particular classifications; graduate assistants and teaching fellows, 1963-1968; "Draft Outline for Annual Report of University" from C.H. Peake, March 1967; J.A. Kehl to Deans on projected SLA enrollment for 1968-1969; appraisal program-office employees; letters from Chairman Wallace to P. Cross, H. Klug, A. Bothner concerning continuation of adjunct professorships when Mellon Institute and Carnegie Institute of Technology merge; draft of news release on Spectroscopy Lab and the new director, Dr. Foil A. Miller; practice followed concerning training and evaluation of teaching performance of graduate assistants; correspondence on THEMIS proposals; "Request for Development funds for the Chemistry Dept." in support of a new Spectroscopy Laboratory and a computerized library to serve as a Chemical Information Center; Department Chairman meetings, September 1966-May 1967.
- Chemistry - Search for Head, 1961-1963 (Box 4, Folder 27)
- Computer Science, 1965-1967 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  Proposal for the creation of a Computer Science Program, Dean Halliday and Hollscher to Edison Montgomery; Computer time; memo on National Science Foundation Computer Funds and NSF publication "Instructional Scientific Equipment Program"; Curriculum vitae of Jules Mersel who was being considered for a faculty and/or research appointment.
- Crystallography, 1964-1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  Correspondence on consideration of joint work with Veterans Administration Hospital; memo from Dean Halliday to chairman requesting information about the involvement of faculty and students with foreign countries, 1966; renovation for Thaw Hall.
- Geology, 1958-1960 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  Development of the department; correspondence on estimation of cost for installing a visual recording unit for the seismograph, 1949; correspondence on whether field work is considered basic research; correspondence on "Geology Department Appraisal of its Use of Teaching Resources"; position inquiries; course information; invitation to XXL Intl. Geology Congregation; record of earthquake in Rocky Mountain area on Pitt seismograph; letters about excellent teaching of Martin S. Bender; Dr. Norman K. Flint recommended for position at St. U. College of Education, New Paltz, N.Y.; students and student participation in development of graduate correspondence; disposition of George Hubbard Clapp Seismograph.
- Geology, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  Request for support for research; employment inquiry; good teaching vs. research for promotion; comments on seismograph station; acknowledgment of gift of equipment by Gulf Research; department staff meeting minutes, September-October 1961; handling of research contract information; Bermuda Program (University of Pittsburgh and Bermuda Biological Station); report to National Science Foundation by Committee on Biological Oceanography.
- Geology, 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  Departmental course schedules, Winter and Spring 1961/1962; proposal for an "Open Ocean" course in Oceanography; correspondence on closing of seismograph station; "Graduate Work in Geology at the University of Pittsburgh"; proposal outlining plans and materials needed for improved instruction in Geology; "Research in Geology Related to Space Problems"; personnel to head geophysical program.
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  Overtures to Paul Benedum for funds (Benedum gives $19,400 to initiate research in Earth Magnetism); George M. Bevier gifts to Pitt; staff meeting minutes, July 1963; change of name of department; University of Pittsburgh participation in U.S.-Japan Scientific Cooperation Program; Cooperative Program in Earth Sciences: Pitt-CIT; course schedule, Spring 1963; proposal for TV course in Earth and Planetary Science; "Visiting Program Brochure for Visiting Schools 1962-1963" University of Kansas; memos on Interdisciplinary Programs.
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1963-1964 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  Gulf Research diving surplus machine tools; Oceanographic Programs; inquiries about openings; recruitment; Cooperative Program in Earth Sciences: Pitt-CIT and Penn State; Interdisciplinary program in Crystallography; use of Alumni Hall.
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1963-1964 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  Advisory Committee for the Department; Bermuda Program and relationship with CIT; "The Birth of a New Geophysical and Oceanography Program for the Pittsburgh Region" paper; fundraising for programs; notes on Earth-Tide Program "Project Lambert."
- Earth and Planetary Science - Oceanography Program, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 36)
- Earth and Planetary Science, 1964-1965 (Box 5, Folder 37)